The Insurance Ombudsman has
released its annual report, which
shows separate data for each health insurance company.  How many complaints have been registered
and how many of them have been
resolved.  In today's video,
using this data,
I want to show you a total of four to five insights
which are very important for us and you as a policy holder.
First of all, I will
show you the trend of these complaints which shows that there has been an increase in
complaints in health insurance in the last few years.
What is that in percentage?  After that I will
tell you that out of the complaints registered with the
insurance company, how many percent of these
complaints have been decided in favor of the policy holder
and how many percent of the complaints have been
decided in favor of the insurance company.
After that I
will also show you the data of top 15 health insurance companies.
How many complaints have been registered and how many have been
settled and how many complaints have
gone in favour of the policy holders and
how many in favour of the insurance company so that
we can know whether the
intervention of the Insurance Ombudsman is of any benefit
or not and finally the substantive data comes
that if any one health insurance company has
disbursed a claim of ₹1000 in the entire year.
How much of that money did the policy
holders have to recover by complaining?   That
is, we will also know from which health insurance company it is
most difficult to withdraw money.
Before we
start the video, I would like to tell you one more thing.
I know very well that you
love videos very much.  I
like it very much.  I see this in your comments.
But data shows that
more than 90% of the viewers have
not subscribed to the channel.  Now let's go, okay.
I don't say subscribe repeatedly or at the beginning.
This does
n't mean you should forget to subscribe.
So first subscribe to the channel
, press the notification bell and
then let's move towards the data.   The
data on health insurance related complaints filed with Insurance Ombudsman from April 1, 2024 to March 31, 2025, as per the annual report,
is shown here.  The total number of complaints
registered was 37431, out of which
77.5%
complaints have been resolved.
Approximately 29,000
complaints have already been resolved.   The
total relief amount comes to ₹151 crore.   A
total of ₹151 crore has been given by the
companies through complaints from all the health insurance companies.
These claims were not approved directly.
This money has been received after the intervention of the Insurance Ombudsman.  22.5% complaints
are still pending.  An estimated 8,500 complaints are
still in process.  On which no
decision has been taken yet.  Out of the total complaints
registered during this entire year,
how many percent of customers have got relief
?  That means, how many complaints have been decided
in the customer's favor?  So that
percentage is 53.6%, that is, the
decision of 53 complaints out of 100
came in favor of the policy holder and the health
insurance companies had to pay the money.
Which includes the amount of recommendations and awards
which is written here.
I will tell you what is recommendation and
award
in insurance oddsman, I will tell you that later.   The
cases in which the policyholder did not get relief constitute
46.4% of the total overall disposed cases, i.e., these are the cases in which the
decision came in the company's favor as per the
policy contract.  The thing to note here is
that in these 13500 cases the
decision did not come in favor of the policy holder.  There are
also cases where
customers withdrew or there
was a jurisdiction issue that the Ombudsman
cannot decide on.  Mutual settlements were done.  The
insurance company and the customer have reached a
settlement regarding some amount.   This
means that this 46.4% includes all types of cases
in which the policy holder did
not receive the money through the Insurance Ombudsman.
Whether those cases were withdrawn or
settled or the Ombudsman did
not give a decision in favour, all together they amount
to 46.4% of the cases.  So, the number of
cases in which the customer got relief is 53.6% and the number in
which the customer did not get relief is 46.4%.  Including
all the categories which I have mentioned
earlier.  The second data I
want to show you is the trend of complaints year wise.
These are just complaints about health insurance.
In the financial year 2022-23, the total number of
complaints was 25873,
in the year 2023-24 the number of complaints increased to
and in 2024-25 the number of complaints
increased even more.  Total complaints
registered are 32655 complaints during the entire financial
year.  That means,
if we look between 2022-23 to 24-25, there is an increase of 26%
in complaints.  Now what is the reason for this?  It is
not that the company did not do wrong before.
Awareness plays a major role in this.  Now
people know that through social media, through
channels like ours or through other people who are
working in the space, they get to
know and understand what
their rights are.
More people approach the Insurance
Ombudsman knowing where they can lodge a complaint and how to do so.  So, the problems and
complaints which used to remain suppressed earlier are now
reaching the Insurance Ombudsman.
Friends, this data is very interesting.  In this
I will show you the total complaints of the top 15 health insurance companies.  I
will tell you how many of those complaints have been resolved
and we will also see how many are pending.
So the highest marker will be
visible to you at the top.  Star Health
Insurance has total complaints of 12186
in just one year 2024-25 which is the
highest in the industry.  Out of this,
approximately 9860 complaints have been resolved
and around 2300 complaints are still pending.
Second comes Care Health
Insurance, with a total of 4423 complaints, out of which
3233 complaints have been resolved.  There are
currently around 1200 complaints pending.
Third is Neema Bhupa.   There
are 3983 complaints.  Out of which
around 3200 complaints have been resolved.   Have been
disposed of.  Pending is 786.
Aditya Birla comes fourth.  2354
complaints, 1803 have been resolved.  551
are remaining till the end of financial year 2024-25.
Now you must have noticed one thing.  I
noticed that the first four companies are stand-
alone health insurance companies.  Those who have
only health insurance business.
Irrespective of their portfolio size,
regardless of how many
policies they have sold.  The highest number of complaints have been
seen against these top four companies.
In 2024-25.  The market share of National Insurance, New
India Insurance, New India
Insurance is
more than Star Health Insurance
in terms of claim settlement.  But
the complaints are reasonable and less.  There
are 1706 complaints out of which 1200 have been resolved
and only 522 are pending.
HDFC Ergo is one of the favourites of policy
holders.  Total complaints are 1542,
1117 have been disposed of and 425 are
still pending.  By the end of the financial year.
Till now Oriental Insurance has 1450 complaints.  Out of which
around 1100 complaints have been
resolved.  There are very few complaints about ICIC LBRD.  There
are 974 complaints.  723 have been
disposed of.  And 251 were pending
till the end of the financial year.
If we talk about Tata IG, there were 822 complaints.  595
complaints have been disposed of.  227
complaints are pending.  Reliance General
Insurance 711 Complaints.  Manipal Singhana has
687 complaints, Bajaj Allianz has 676 complaints,
SBI General has only 568 complaints.
So from here you can understand how many
complaints were registered.  How many of them have been
resolved and how many are pending.
You should not take a decision on
which company is better on the basis of this data.  Because
you are going to see more important and
interesting insights in the upcoming data.
Now let's talk about the resolution time, that is, out of the
complaints registered with the Insurance Ombudsman
in the financial year 2024-25,
78.6% complaints were resolved within 3
months of filing the complaint.
22,791 complaints were resolved within 3 months of filing the complaint.  It
took 3 to 12 months to resolve 4343 complaints
and more than a year is being taken to resolve
1883 complaints.   That
means, now as the workload
increases on the Insurance Ombudsman, the Insurance Lokpal, the
timeline for settlement of this number of complaints may increase a little.  This
means that it may take time for your complaint to be resolved.
Now friends, this
data will show you how many recommendations and how many awards are there out of the money that the insurance
observers have got from the insurance company to the
policy holders from the health insurance company.
So
let us first understand the difference between recommendation and award.
See, whenever we
file a complaint with the Insurance Ombudsman,
documents of both the parties are taken.  Both are talked to.
Hearing takes place online.
What does the insurance ombudsman provide after that?
Gives recommendations.  Recommendation means that
after looking at all the facts, I
feel that the insurance company should give this money to the
policy holder.  The amount that is released
after accepting that recommendation
is
₹87.69 crore.  This is written here in lakhs.
But I am telling you in crores.  The
amount is ₹87 crore 69 lakh.  The total
such recommendations were ₹9423.
But there are some cases where
Umbsman said you should give this money
to the policy holder.
But the company says no, we do
not agree to this.  So after that, again a
period of 3 months is taken in which the
Insurance Ombudsman again
reviews all the documents and
after that the decision taken by the Insurance Ombudsman
and says that the insurance company will have to
give this money to you is called award.
So, the
decisions taken through Insurance Hombertsman Awards
were approximately 6126 cases in which
money worth around Rs 63.53 crore was released.
Total cases in which health insurance
companies had to pay money to policy holders.  There
are approximately 15,000 cases and a total
compensation relief of Rs 151 crore 26 lakh has been received through the
intervention of the Insurance Ombudsman.
If there was no Insurance Ombudsman or if the
policy holders had not complained against the health insurance companies and had
not stood up for their rights, then this ₹151 crore would have been
refused to be given by the health insurance companies.
Now as we move forward in this video
, the data will become more and more interesting.
This chart will show you
how many decisions were
decided in favor of the insurance company
and how many were decided in favor of the policyholder in each health insurance company.
Meaning, if I
filed a complaint against my health insurance company with the Insurance Observer
that I should get this claim of ₹ lakh, did
I get it or not?  That means the
percentage of every health insurance company is
shown here.  How many decisions came in his favour
and how many came against him.  First of all,
if we talk about Star Health, then
59.6% of the decisions have been in favor of the customers and 40% of the
decisions were such in which things went in favor of the company
or the complaint was withdrawn
or whatever the reason is, the
policy holder did
not get the money from the insurance home Budsman.  If we talk about Care Health, the
ratio is the same 52:47.  52% of the
people got their money.
If we talk about Neemupa, policy holders have got relief in 56% of the cases.
If we talk about
Aditya Birla Health Insurance Company,
then in 70% of the cases, the decisions have been in favor of the policy holder
and in 30% of the cases, the
complaints of the insurance company or whatever else were
not resolved, that is 30% of the cases.
In National Insurance it is almost equal,
around 50-50%.
Under New India Insurance, 58% of the policy holders have not received any relief
and 42% have received relief.  Now
you might be looking at this data in the sense
that the company whose green line is higher, i.e. the
decision has been given in favor of the policy holder,
that company is good.  It's not like that.  Here it
is the reverse.  I would like to tell you to
look at it from this angle.  Here
we take the example of SBI General.  Now see,
here customers have got relief in only
31.8%
cases.  Relief has not been received in 68%
of the cases.  This means that only
31 out of 100 people received the money
through the insurance observers.  But the
complaints of 68 people have been rejected.
He has withdrawn it or no
decision has been taken on it.  Here you have to
see that the decision which will
go in favor of the insurance company means that the
decision of the insurance company to reject the claim was correct.
That means fewer valid claims have been rejected.
Where this green bar
is higher, it means more valid claims have been
rejected.  Later
this money was returned through Insurance Ombudsman.
Including Star Health, Care Health, Neema
Bupa, Aditya Birla National is at par with National.  All other
companies are fine.  But
these are the only four companies in which
policy
holders have had to get their money through the Insurance Ombudsman.  And if the
Insurance Ombudsman has said so, then it
means that the claim should have been given to them earlier also.
You can also see the remaining percentages here.
Tata EIG is a ratio of 60 and 40.
Reliance's share is 50-50.   The
approximate map of SNA is also 50-50.
Bajaj Ali's price is Rs 5248.
You have already seen that of SBI General, it is Rs 6831.  Apart from this,
ICICI LBD is of Rs 6435.  So this time
from the graph we come to know that the companies whose
green bar is above are bigger.  This means
they have rejected fair claims.
Later, after the intervention of the Insurance Observer,
this money was received by the policy holders.
Now friends, company wise data
of top 15 health insurance companies is available as to how many complaints were registered, how much
money was received and percentages etc. If you
want, I can explain it.  My only
fear is that the video might become too long.
So let me do that.  Please comment
whether you want to see it or not.
I do this, I
explain it quickly.  I won't spend much time on this
so we can look at the next data.   First of all
we have selected Star Health Insurance.  There
are total 12,186 complaints.  Of which 9860 have been resolved.   That
means, still 19% complaints
were pending in which relief was given in 59% cases in
which percentage wise it has been told
how much relief was given and in how many cases it was
not given.  Apart from this, how many claims were
settled within 3 months?  Approximately 7700
claims have been settled.  The
amount received in the recommendation is estimated to be ₹6.5 crore and
₹15 crore.  Around ₹16 crores has been received
through awards.
Star Health Insurance alone has a total of Rs 52 crore.
That means Star Health Insurance has to pay a total of Rs 52 crore 45 lakh
due to
Insurance Ombudsman Intervention.  Now
Comes Care Health Insurance.
Total complaints registered under Care Health Insurance were
4400 out
of which 27% complaints were pending.   There
is a huge amount of pending complaints.
Within these 3 months 2500 complaints were resolved.  The
total amount
that this company had to pay to the policy holders through complaints
is ₹18 crore.  Let's talk about Nivapa.
Total complaints of Nivapa Health Insurance Company were
3983.  ₹3197 resolved.  786 were pending.
You can see this percentage of relief.
And including recommendations and awards,
they have given a total of ₹23 crores
to the policy holders.  Next comes Aditya Birla.   The
total complaints stood at 2354 in 2024-25,
of which 23.5% complaints were pending at
the end of the financial year and relief was provided in 70%
of the cases.  That means this money should have been
received at the time of claim.  But later the
policy holders had to take action through intervention.  The
total amount they have paid
to policy holders after these complaints is ₹15.5 crore.
Now let's see friends, HDFC
Arco had a total of ₹150 complaints.  The
relief ratio is 50-50%.  Apart from this,
925 complaints were solved within 3 months and there are
only 63 complaints which are taking more than 1 year.
He has given a total of Rs 6 crore 27 lakh.  And
almost 50-50% of the complaints have been decided in favor of the policy holder and the company.  Let's
talk about ICIC LBRD.  A
total of 974 complaints have been registered within ICICI LBA.  Out
of which 74% complaints have been resolved.
Here 64% of the decisions
went in favor of the company and 35% in favor of the policy holder.  Why so
?  Because here the
insurance company had very strict
observation regarding the terms and conditions of the policy.  That
is, when he
rejected the claim in the first instance, the insurance observer also remained firm on the same decision
in most of the cases.  That
means
claims were not rejected without checking.  These claims were rejected as per the policy terms
and conditions and guidelines.  That
means the
insurance
Ombudsman also kept the same rejection decision.  The total relief
they had to pay was ₹72 crore rupees for the entire
financial year 2024-25.
Talking about Tata AIG, there were only 822
complaints out of which 227 are pending.   There are
many pending complaints and in
only 40% of the complaints the
decision came in the customer's favor and they
actually got their money.  Here he has given
₹1 crore 82 lakh 60% in favor of the
insurance company and 40% in favor of the
policy holder.  If we talk about Bajaj Ali
General Insurance, it has now become Bajaj General
Insurance but earlier it was Bajaj
Alians.  Total complaints are 676 out of
which 78% have been resolved.  The
relief ratio is 50:50% and they have
given total claims worth ₹5 crore after
resolution of these complaints.  Talking about SBI General,
here also 68%
decisions have gone in favor of the company.  That means the company's
decision was right in most cases.  The claim
which he rejected.
He has made a total payment of ₹1.5 crore after the
complaints.  Now let us take a look at some of the government
companies.
What's inside New India Insurance
?  Total complaints are 1706.  If you
look at their market size, there are
very few complaints as compared to the total claim amount they pay.  Of which
30% are still pending.  This takes a lot of time
because these are government companies, so a lot of time is
spent in them.  60% of the
decisions have come in favor of the company.  Approximately 42% of the money
in favor of the policy holders is Rs. 3 crore
46 lakhs. After complaining, they have
given money to the policy holders.
If we talk about United India, there were a total of 876
complaints and here also 60% were
in favor of the company or the complaints were withdrawn
and the total amount given by them is
₹1 crore 71 lakh out of ₹151
crore of total relief amount which was given in the entire year.
Now friends, the last and
most interesting data comes that out of the
total claims given by every health insurance company to the
policy holders in the whole year,
how much money the policy holders had to pay by filing complaints,
I will show you that data.  One
is this bargraph and apart from this there is another bargraph in
which I will tell you the percentage.
That will give a little more clarity.  So
these are the top five companies from which
policy holders have received the maximum amount of money after complaints.  If we talk about
Star Health Insurance,
they have given total claims of ₹173 crores.  ₹173 crore
is a huge amount.  Out of this, the amount of relief that the
police holder had to take through Ombsman is only ₹52 crore.
If you look at it individually, ₹52 crores becomes a
lot.  But if you
look at the overall disbursement of claims out of Rs
11,000 crore, then ₹50
crore is nothing.  If we
talk about NIMAPA, then it has given total claims of ₹3291 crore to
its policy holders
without any complaint. Out of the settlement done directly in the hospital,
approximately ₹24 crore has been taken by the
policy holders through complaints.
If we talk about Care Health,
total claims worth ₹4851 crore have been disbursed.
Out of ₹18 crore, ₹1.5 crore has been
borne by the policy holders through complaints.  Whereas in Aditya Birla
Health Insurance, a total of ₹2578 crore was
disbursed in claims, out of which
₹12.5 crore was
paid to the policy holders through complaints and similarly
in HDFC Ergo General Insurance, claims worth ₹4389
crore were paid and only ₹10 crore was
paid to the policy holders through complaints.  Now here if you calculate such ratios then it will become
difficult to understand.   Let
me show you another chart here
which will make it absolutely clear to you.
Total Disbursed
Amount vs Amount Disbursed through
Insurance of Birdsman Complaints in
202425 in Star Health Insurance If they calculate the ratio then I will
explain it to you in simple language.  This is
0.470%.
This means that if
Star Health Insurance has settled ₹1000
claims directly in a whole year, out of that
only ₹4 or we can say ₹5 have to be
borne by the policy holders through complaints.
If we talk about ₹5 out of 1000, then
policy holders have to bear ₹5 out of 1000 through complaints.
If we talk about Care Health,
when the policy holders received the claim of Rs 1000 directly,
approximately Rs 4 had to be recovered by filing a complaint.
₹4 out of 1000 is a very low percentage.
If we look at the overall claims, but if there are
complaints then there is more noise about that thing.
We complain about that thing a
lot.  Because the person who gets the claim does
not go anywhere and tweet.   I do
n't feel like I have received the claim anywhere.
But the data shows that claims are being received.
In Aditya Birla Health Insurance also, the policy holder had to
collect ₹5 out of the total amount of ₹1000 through complaint.
And
this figure is the lowest in HDFC Ergo.  That means,
when HDFC Ergo paid the claim of ₹1000 directly, out of that
only ₹1.500 had to be taken by the police holders
by complaining to the Insurance Ombudsman.
So friends,
after seeing this data of complaints of Insurance Ombudsman, what did you notice
which I could not discuss here in the video.
What did you understand?
What trend did you notice?  Please do
tell me that by commenting.  Because you
can use this data as much as you want.   You
can understand the companies as much as you want in a better way and if you want to use this data then I will mention the
entire annual report and
these selected pages.
You will also find that link in the description.  By going to
that report you
can directly access those pages.
You will get all this data from there.
I have just presented that data to
you in a slightly presentable manner
so that you can easily understand this data and
know the status of complaints of your health insurance companies well.
If you liked this video and information, then to
show your love and support,
please like the video and subscribe to the channel.  Brothers, people are watching but are
not subscribing.  I don't speak
in the beginning.  This does not mean that you
forget.  Please subscribe to the channel.
Because nothing is going to be different from this.  Only
YouTube will promote it.  This
information will reach more people.  Apart from this it has
no meaning.  So please subscribe to the
channel and the biggest
benefit of subscribing will be that you will get similar real time data
based informative videos
in the future also.  You will
also get a notification.  So please press the bell icon also.
I am Harvinder Singh, see you
in the next video.  Till then take care,
stay fit and stay healthy.